Every single time you go up for a
pre-training run, you're about to put in
more flops into this run than you've
ever done before.
>> This is Vlad Feinberg. He's Google
DeepMind's [music] pre-training area
lead, and I asked him all about how to
get a job at a frontier lab.
>> That was a particular skill that I see
voracious demand for across all the
different labs. The research skill set
is going to become increasingly
important. If you do the scaling book
exercises and, you know, send me a video
of yourself doing them, I would love to,
you know, interview you.
>> Here's the full episode.
You wrote this post that was titled "How
to get a job at a frontier lab." What
are the skills that are kind of in
demand on frontier labs? Maybe we can
talk about the shape of the work.
There's quite a range of different
things that frontier labs require.
At this point, LLMs are artifacts that
are connected to,
uh, research and product in ways that
machine learning really hasn't been as
connected to before. And so, it it
really touches on so many different
things. The goal of my post was to
propose just a couple tangible
directions in which labs could require a
certain set of skills not not to be
fully exhaustive.
And really the ones that I I dive into
have to do with uh kernel development
and low-level engineering to accelerate
the runtime for these LLMs, uh, in
practice. And so, that that was a
particular skill that I see voracious
demand for across all the different
labs, uh, and uh among different
projects within the labs. So, that that
seemed like a very sharp one to call out
as, uh,
uh an overall need. Uh, and so
specifically
whenever we're doing a research project
that involves
changing the architecture for the neural
net in a particular way or rethinking
how we might do serving to
uh you know, do better KV caching or
something like that.
Again, across the stack, you just need
to be able to implement these new
techniques in efficient ways and
uh the inner loop of all of these
different changes is creating software
artifacts that can function at large
scales with high throughput, low
latency.
Uh and this is just fundamental work
that's tied to classical back-end
engineering thinking.
Uh so, yeah, it seemed like a very
open thing for people to specialize in.
>> My friends that work at OpenAI and
Anthropic, there's this distinction of
an applied org and the research org. I
was wondering if DeepMind has a similar
uh distinction and if you could speak
about what that difference is.
>> Uh so, we we have different focus areas
and like
you know, for instance, within GDM,
there's a team that focuses on how
uh we can use our Gemini LLMs to better
inform search results. And so, like that
might be
some, you know,
you know, in some way like an applied
version of the LLMs, but I I
am hesitant to, you know, make a very
sharp distinction here because there's
so much
actual like hard research that has to go
into
this kind of level of product
integration. Like specifically for the
one I mentioned, uh quite a lot of work
goes into making sure that these LLMs
are factual and can cite sources uh to
have very precise grounded answers,
assessing the quality of these sources
to make sure that you're not referring
to anything that's like sarcastic or a
joke.
This is
I guess a good example of how even in
like product specific quote unquote
applied AI verticals, you're still doing
research.
That being said, there's definitely
what I would say is like very classical
LLM research teams, pre-training,
post-training.
These are things that are still
stand-alone teams inside of GDM that are
focused on
what I would say is like, you know,
creating soda models, you know, pure
research.
Again, the caveat is
the the pure research that we do, like
the extent that it matters is the extent
to which we can realize it. And so, you
know, we're just as responsible with uh
delivering these models and making sure
they train stably and actually
being like the SREs of sorts for the
training run to make sure that the model
training is going smoothly
as we are for coming up with the recipes
to make these LLMs.
And you can't separate those two roles.
It's it's really crucial to kind of wear
both of those hats. So,
yeah, I think you can you can draw up a
spectrum between research and applied,
but no matter what in today's world, I
think
everyone needs to be fluid across that
spectrum.
>> I notice there's also another spectrum
of software engineer to pure AI
researcher and like how do you think of
that spectrum? Like software engineering
versus like AI researcher roles?
>> So, I guess in
in in my case specifically, I think a
lot of
what we do
and a lot of the new techniques that we
develop,
the groundwork is laid in infrastructure
investment. So, um I
can walk through what my team does a
little bit more detail later, but
one of the verticals is distillation.
And in order to do uh distillation, it's
it's some way of uh
transferring the knowledge or some form
of statistics about the underlying data
set through a teacher model into the
student model to make the student model
better than if it hadn't ever seen these
auxiliary statistics from the teacher.
And when you're talking about statistics
derived from a massive LLM applied to
trillions and trillions of tokens,
uh you're talking about a level of flops
investment that, you know, is
you know, millions and millions of
dollars. And
that in turn
means that you have to be able to think
through
how do you
uh
optimize the system to be as efficient
as possible because every operation that
we're performing is is multiplied by
such a large factor that every second
counts, every byte of storage counts,
and
quite a bit of that work
is
you know, good old-fashioned software
engineering. And so,
uh in particular,
the infrastructure for distillation has
evolved
through maybe three [snorts] to four
generations at this point.
And in each one,
we've taken a step back, looked at what
kind of research methods have we been
applying for distillation holistically,
thought about how do we broaden what the
infrastructure is capable of, and
there's definitely a couple discrete
points where rethinking the system
design of how we perform distillation
enables us to do research on
distillation methods much more quickly.
And so it's this kind of investment that
like okay, this like four-month or
whatever rewrite of our distillation
infrastructure
then results in a dramatically new and
understanding of distillation scaling
laws that translates to really strong
models. So
it really just work across the stack and
I you know, I can't
Yeah, I can't imagine that we would have
gotten results like flash 3.0 without
having made those distillation
infrastructure investments that are at
the end of the day things that started
with a good old-fashioned design doc and
thinking about what the right
abstractions are for
generating these teacher statistics,
coming up with the right storage system
for them, thinking through what could
support the reading and writing across
multiple different data centers at the
scale.
Really classical distributed systems
problems.
>> Yeah, I mean it sounds like there's
there's a lot of software engineering
back-end infra type problems given just
the scale of the computer at this point.
It still feels like though there at some
point in that spectrum there's some
crossover where there's these new skills
like somewhere where if you had you took
arbitrary back-end engineer and you
place them to I don't know, adjust the
model architecture or something. Like
there that is like a bit of a jump more
than the infra work.
Like how do you see that distinction?
>> Yeah, so I think there is a crossover
point in terms of doing research where
research is an endeavor where the
payoffs become a lot higher risk higher
reward and
we have this notion of
uh kind of research taste, which is, you
know, some high-level intuition about
what path you should be proceeding
through the DAG of the multiple uh
different milestones that you need to
accomplish in a particular project.
In some sense, we can view software
engineering projects through a similar
DAG where, you know, you have all of
these intermediate artifacts that you
want to hit in a software program to uh
get to the final result. But, in the
software engineering case, the DAG is
more or less deterministic where you,
you know, build one service, then a
different service, then a third service,
and you know, you figure out your
storage infrastructure layer first, uh
that kind of thing, and you can just
make monotone progress. But, in the
research case, you have to
uh kind of explore this DAG, which is
now stochastic, cuz some of the nodes,
which might be some research ideas or
some, you know, aspect of getting to a
final goal, uh may or may not work out.
And I think that requires a bit of a
mindset shift.
And that that kind of mindset shift
takes a while to learn, and it takes
specialized skills to learn.
Uh this would be the kind of skills you
pick up in a PhD, for instance.
One succinct way I could put it,
there's a really excellent post by
this uh Professor Jacob Steinhardt, and
I I love to frame a lot of the research
work that I do in this way, and it's
research as an MDP.
So, MDP here, Markov decision process,
uh it's again, we have this high-level
idea of a stochastic dependency graph
between different milestones in a
research project where you might need to
have a pertinent certain kind of result
or prove a certain kind of theorem
before you get to a certain kind of
conclusion. Uh similarly, for a machine
learning research project, you might
need to have this and that
featureization working before where can
get this and that
ImageNet accuracy or something like
that. Um
and expanding those nodes in this graph,
it it's this stochastic endeavor where
these approaches may or may not work
out, and whether or not
one works out opens up a set of new
possibilities for you.
And so
the approach that you might have in
the software engineering case where
you could fully write out here are all
the paths to the goal
across walking this graph, what's the
shortest path to your goal?
That approach is not optimal in the
research case because if all of a sudden
the transitions between the edges in
this graph become unreliable, and uh
some of the nodes you might not even
be aware of. It might be a hidden MDP.
Then, the way that you might approach
this problem
would really differ. And in particular,
you have to factor in the success rate
and the time investment that you're
going to be putting into
uh these different research ideas,
as well as
a priori estimating what those different
rates are. And that's a very different
exercise than writing up what the, you
know, design for your software
engineering project might be. And it's
it it's this skill set of of building an
intuition of how likely an approach is
to work out without having yet done that
approach
that I think people
often you know, correlate with this uh
research taste notion.
But that's exactly the one that you need
to build up in order to properly
uh traverse this MDP.
>> For the the research projects, and just
like generally the nature of the
research work, I mean, it sounds like
you're you're saying that there's a lot
more uncertainty here. I'm still trying
to get a sense of the the nature of the
work. If you threw this back-end
engineer into a team that's doing
research. Like, what are those like
concrete examples where they fall short?
>> Like, I think the the very first thing
that comes to mind is having the right
context for the research landscape in
which you're operating. So,
quite a bit of research work involves
like
almost uh
this kind of
um you have to take on this like very
humble viewpoint of there's been quite a
lot of investment in related work in the
past. And until I know
the sum total of humanity's bleeding
edge in this topic, I'm definitely not
going to be able to further that
bleeding edge. So, building up uh
a solid understanding of of past work uh
in a particular area
uh and doing that related literature
review is maybe the first thing that I
would imagine people might stumble on is
uh
having read and having the skills to
effectively traverse, you know,
historical uh citation tree for a
particular topic. Because you don't have
the time to read all of these different
papers. You need to build up a sense of
uh what are the high value papers and
what are the ways in which I can assess
if a paper's worth reading without fully
reading it. That's like the first thing
that comes to mind as the you know,
skill that people need to build up. Even
to be able to read these research-level
papers, you have to have a background in
machine learning, in um some, you know,
computer science, and
uh
you know, depending on the paper and
depending on the domain, there might be
all sorts of prerequisites in terms of
like the underlying math and
coursework that you would want to have
to properly understand. So,
that's that's quite important to be able
to have a deep understanding of what
methodology is available because you
really won't have
a lot of hope of improving upon the
methodology if you don't understand
what's there already. So, so I think I
like mentioned earlier, one of the
things that my team works on is is
distillation.
And in order to
advance our
understanding in uh distillation for
large language models,
you have to have a good understanding of
like what we're trying to do with LLMs.
And uh just to give a cursory overview
here, the name of the game for LLM
research is
especially in pre-training is uh is
scaling laws. And so,
what are scaling laws? People focus a
lot about like, you know, this power law
structure and the fact that like you,
you know, have this and that exponent,
but like what matters is less so the
functional form. What matters is
for a given recipe of scaling up your
LLM, so as you invest more and more
flops into the pre-training run of an
LLM,
you have to be able to predict what the
final test loss of this LLM is going to
be. And why why do we care about this
question? Why do we care about
predicting what our uh generalization
error is?
In the classical machine learning world,
like say we're trying to, you know, win
ImageNet.
We have our test loss, which is our
classification uh error for, you know, a
thousand different classes and uh you
run your VGG or your ResNet proposal to
get that uh classification error. That's
an estimate of how well that model does
at classifying
amongst those thousand classes uh
various different images.
We can estimate how good our method's
going to be by taking a validation set
and then whenever we have an
architecture idea for a neural net, we
just train it and then we
uh do a bunch of uh validation set runs
and we get a cross-validation error that
is itself an estimator of our final test
error. And so in this way you can just
iterate on different ideas
uh through this process.
But what's different in LLM world is
every single time you go up for a
pre-training run, you're about to put in
more flops into this run than you've
ever done before.
So, it's in some sense like a one-shot
version of this ImageNet problem. You
never get to see the full ImageNet
training data set. You have to practice
on MNIST and then CIFAR and then maybe
based off of those, you try to come up
with a method that just works right off
the bat on ImageNet. And if you were to
just do that by itself, as I'm sure many
people have tried, uh like certainly
when I was learning how to do all of
those different things, you get
something, it works really great on
MNIST, it maybe even works on CIFAR, and
then all of a sudden it breaks on
ImageNet.
You'll find out that like things don't
just generalize easily across scale like
this. And
so much of what we do for LLMs is coming
up with recipes, where a recipe is this
function that goes from number of flops
you'd like to train on to a training
routine for this LLM. And if you can
couple this recipe with a prediction
rule that can predict accurately what
your LLM accuracy is going to be, then
um you're able to make decisions about
how to improve your recipe cuz you can
use that prediction.
That is all a ton of context on what uh
LLM research looks like in general, but
that's like a an understanding that we
got to, that we even thought was
feasible, thanks to so much uh
initial LLM scaling work that we've seen
across the Kaplan paper, across
Chinchilla.
Since those two papers, there's been a
lot more work in terms of like what
other factors are there beyond uh number
of params and um
number of tokens that you train on that
influence your prediction accuracy.
Uh like number of unique tokens for
instance.
But like I would say like those two
foundational papers for LLMs, uh those
are informed by uh an even even longer
line of uh different uh scaling works
going back to like say the original uh
GPTs and then Google has had a ton of
scaling work across its Palm papers.
This is just a set of works that have
informed that viewpoint that I described
earlier that
you you kind of just need to build up by
having gone through that literature
review yourself.
>> If you were for instance, if uh
you were trying to pick someone that was
going on your team and the the way that
you would judge their fitness to help
you push the frontier is their
understanding of the frontier including
the existing literature which requires
all these prerequisite. I think you
called it mathematical maturity in your
post.
>> Yeah, so I think I I
I think it's
easy to read and understand those papers
once you have mathematical maturity.
So I guess the ones I mentioned in
particular nowadays they're table
stakes. So I I would expect candidates
to be familiar with them. Um
I think um
the the general skill set is being able
to dive in to
uh a paper of that level and then
understanding it.
Uh
you know being able to take a research
idea uh from a paper and implementing it
yourself. Like that's that's just a a
very important skill set to be able to
have. Like we get, you know,
all sorts of uh uh different ideas
presented, you know,
they might not all directly apply to our
domain, but if you can deeply understand
them, then you can iterate on them, and
you can improve them inside of
uh inside of our domain. And so, when we
assess for people who can work with the
mathematical concepts in these machine
learning papers, that's that's I guess
the the key skill there that would be
evidence that you can go pick up this
arbitrary paper and see to what extent
these ideas carry over uh in the Google
setting.
>> This probably won't be exhaustive, but
I'd be curious to hear other domains
that maybe people could dig into to see
what kind of matters in frontier AI
research. So, you'd mentioned
distillation, you also mentioned
kernels, it sounds like kernels are
helpful everywhere. Um but are there
other areas that come to mind if you
were just raffle off areas that are not
necessarily exhaustive?
>> One thing that I think is is quite
powerful is uh actually
programming language research. So, by
looking into how we can create
abstractions at the programming language
level, we could facilitate kernel
development. I think ThunderKittens is a
really good example of this. Like,
coming up with an
an abstraction that allows you to write
kernels through four functions instead
of arbitrary globs of C++ code uh
allows you to move really quickly uh in
uh developing algorithms that fully
utilize hardware.
So, like, it it at that point it it's um
it's not about the PL research itself,
it's about having a passion for,
you know, these kind of programming
language abstractions and and working
with uh low-level hardware.
Um you know, uh people who, you know,
are interested in and will
try to work with like cute DSL, the this
kind of thing where there's a lot of
hardware specific domain specific
languages. Uh one other thing that comes
to mind besides PL and uh scaling law
literature would be reinforcement
learning literature.
Uh so in particular ever since uh RLHF,
uh I think we've seen that
deep RL algorithms uh like PPO do have a
place in production systems and you
know, there was a time where
that was in question, but uh now it's
you know,
uh pretty unanimous that we see these
kind of algorithms applied to real
production systems and
the uh theory behind that uh you kind of
have to start with the basics for
reinforcement learning and work their
way up to
you know, the myriad uh value-based
methods and and uh policy gradient
methods that we have today.
That's that's another domain that I
think is just like a very rich
literature tree to crawl. Um and then
for more of the back end engineer folks,
just beyond just the kernels themselves,
there's I think
a pretty fun overlap between distributed
systems and optimization work where uh
figuring out how to design neural net
training algorithms that allow for
training across
many GPUs.
There's all sorts of fun challenges
between asynchronicity, how up-to-date
your gradients are,
how
pipelining affects the staleness,
uh all of these system choices that you
could make in your training algorithm
design will impact convergence and the
final quality of your neural net. And uh
those are things that can be analyzed
independently of the LLM setting
uh and have been for a while. So,
uh, you know, especially if you're kind
of more infra-inclined, then having a
good understanding of like,
uh, how those different algorithms works
work is a is a really good place to
start.
>> Do you see any difference between the
the demands of the different frontier
labs? So, for instance, if someone wants
to work at DeepMind, is there like a
particular area that you see DeepMind
cares about more than Anthropic, for
instance?
>> I think in terms of the skill set, it's
probably pretty similar. Yeah, I think I
think there's maybe differences in like
business strategy and, uh, you know, the
set of offerings that's a function of,
uh, the specialties of the labs and,
uh, like the kind of different, uh, you
know, customers that the labs could
have. Uh, but
uh, I would say that there's there's
quite a lot of overlap between the labs
in terms of what people look for. And
like, yeah, like when I posted, uh, my
post, you would you would see like, you
know, people from both OpenAI and
Anthropic saying like, yeah, like we
agree with this advice. And so, you
know, I think, um,
that that's just a little bit of
evidence towards that.
>> I think one reason for the the huge
demand for wanting to go closer to AI
research is because people are thinking
of software engineering is not going to
be as important in the future. Is there
a similar thought in when it comes to
research where LLMs is also going to
handle a lot of that work as well, so
there's no reason to favor AI research
versus software engineering?
>> Um,
so I think the the research skill set is
going to become increasingly important.
Uh, so I would say like being able to
handle stochastic components in the
planning of your work
is is just going to be a larger and
larger part of how we approach our jobs.
Figuring out how to leverage AI in
whatever thing you work on, which
doesn't even have to be software
related, is just an important muscle to
start building right away.
Um because these components aren't
deterministic and thinking about how do
I construct systems around these LLMs to
do my job more effectively,
uh that's that's going to be the thing
that sets you apart in the future. And I
think that's true no matter what you're
going to be doing. Look, I think I think
there's there's fud everywhere,
especially with with some of the
approach to marketing that some people
have in terms of AI. It's fud that is
being intentionally leveraged. And so, I
I feel like
people should really just focus on
themselves and and trying to uh be more
productive themselves.
I I don't think that like AI is going to
replace all of our roles. And so, the
reason for that is that
one of the important aspects of what we
do as humans in an organization, which
is really this web of trust,
from like, you know, this organization
that is, you know, this pool of
resources and this pool of people that
manages these resources.
One of the important things that we do
is we allocate those resources towards
cer- certain goals.
And um
even when
we can accelerate
our execution,
there's an element of making decisions
around how we allocate these resources
that will always be
something that needs to be attributable
to a human making that decision.
And uh that's simply because
you can't hand off blame to AI.
So,
we at this point have LLMs that really
deeply understand law. And they could,
you know, review your contract for you
or something like that.
But, they can't represent you in court
because they can't be disbarred.
And so, that's that's I think like a
really, you know, sharp way that I might
describe like, okay, this is why the
legal profession will go on even though
LLMs are really good at recalling
precedent is
you want to have someone who is
responsible who can validate the output
of AI to perform
uh
legal work more effectively for you
rather than
hand off
your legal defense to an LLM.
>> Yeah, I think the FUD, that was actually
the original motivation for your post.
>> Yeah, I mean, I I really think that the
mindset that people should have is is a
constructive one. And so, there was a
tweet that I saw, I think by Didi, that
was like some long-form, you know,
fear-mongering about, you know, uh
uh
AI permanent underclass or something
like that. And uh
it's easy to get stuck in that loop, but
I think the important thing to think
about is like we all have agency over
our future and we can start investing in
uh skills that matter for tomorrow
today. And
um
that's that's really
the only thing you should be doing,
right? Like, you know, worrying about it
is not going to not going to help you.
And so, part of why I wanted to write
this post is is in response to that.
Uh because it it it was something that I
could see echoed, you know, I gave the a
lecture at Princeton a while back and,
you know, a big question that came up is
like, you know, how do I work at
DeepMind? And And it's something that
like uh yeah, just when people find out
what I do, that's the top question
people ask. So, I figured it would be
helpful to add a little bit more
constructive
you know, direction to the discourse
here.
>> One last thing on the post cuz, you
know, if you think about getting a role,
there's obviously the skills and we
talked a lot about the skills and your
fitness for the role, but there's also
kind of the
signaling for that role and like what is
kind of valued if you were to be saying
marketing yourself to one of these
frontier labs, what signals
matter most?
>> Actual evidence that you've created
something of uh
of use to other people along the line of
kernels, right? Like you can take any of
the many open source LLMs that we have
and optimize them. You don't have to
make them better in every case. You
could show that oh, I have an
improvement for this and that setting.
It doesn't even have to be something
that speeds up the model on GPU. There's
all sorts of open source stacks like
vLLM. There's a lot of other
things that you can do besides
accelerating the LLM inference on
device. The serving stack that surrounds
LLMs is a very sophisticated distributed
system that has to maintain
this KB cache memory and deal with
all sorts of like load balancing and
request queuing and and very common
problems for for back-end servers. And
these projects are always looking for
help. So, you know, contributions to
vLLM or SG Lang
or demonstrations with TensorRT.
They have I think a
a distributed system called Dynamo that
allows for disaggregated serving
where
you could show that you you made a
project using these components, you
improved these components. Like that
would be an extremely positive signal
for any candidate that I'm looking at
and and a very welcome contribution to
open source.
>> I think also a lot of what we said is
kind of assuming the path of external
hire into Frontier Lab.
But a lot of these Frontier Labs have
large organizations that aren't
necessarily doing the cutting edge
Frontier work. So let's say yeah, for
instance, I mean, you know, Google
DeepMind versus
let's say there's some infrastructure
eng that's working on search and they
have the back-end skillset, maybe not as
much domain context and they try to
internal transfer to Google DeepMind.
Does any of your advice differ in that
kind of case for like an internal
transfer versus
someone who's coming from external?
>> There's someone who I worked with
closely on the search side
who actually did transfer to my team
Nate Lidzén and he's amazing and now he
owns so much of
like what we do on my team in terms of
inference code design for
like flash and flashlight and
I would say like he's a really great
example of this where
his approach was, you know, how do I
help my PA, my product area
adopt this technology as effectively as
possible. So I think there's, you know,
definitely
if you're
in
organization that isn't directly
generating these models, but in some way
trying to leverage them there's
a very big gap in terms of applying
these LLMs effectively, serving them
effectively
within
your organization
and becoming someone who does that
really effectively not only creates a
ton of value
in terms of like
the uh you know specific business need
for your org which will definitely
elevate you and your org
but it'll also be the case that you're
going to just naturally become the
partner that we work with
on the research side to make sure that
our models are effective within your org
and so at that point you know you may or
may not want to transfer definitely if
you transfer we you know be happy to
work with you but like
at that point I think you're you're
you're already doing something that is
cutting edge which is
integrating this new technology into
you know a real product that people use
and so
yeah that'd be my advice there.
>> As it towards the end of this post as we
as we leave this topic you had the
concrete invitation cuz I know you were
hiring
do you want to say what that was?
>> Yeah so I was just trying to think of
like you know you know how do I put my
money where my mouth is
um
how do I demonstrate look this is good
way to show that you have you know at
least some evidence of of like the the
skills that I called out as important
you know intent mathematical maturity
grit
and so I listed out a couple of
exercises that demonstrate you know some
initial knowledge of scaling laws some
willingness to get into the weeds
engineering wise in terms of
implementing a real transformer
and
sort of willingness to pick up the kind
of bread and butter bread and butter
math that we use every day to size these
LLMs
and you know I won't I won't recall the
full list of like the exercises that I
expected here but like you know if if
you do the detailed like handwritten
version of the scaling book exercises
and you know send me a video of yourself
doing them along with the transformer
exercise on my post
then that's something if you can work in
the uh New York office, I would love to,
you know, interview you for. And quite a
few people reached out to me about that.
I actually already have had a couple
submissions and we're proceeding with
the loop with those people. So,
yeah, it's it's quite a bit of work, but
uh impressively, I got a response within
like, I think,
a week of posting. So,
uh it's definitely doable.
Uh
yeah, I mean, I don't have unlimited
head count, so I mean, the offer's on
the table, but the, you know,
I can only hire so many people. The good
thing is, though, that is such a strong
sign of,
you know, self-development
that uh
not only is this a something that you
should be doing for its own sake,
regardless of whether or not you will
get a job at at DeepMind specifically,
but I think it'll be something that's,
you know,
lets you basically prepare for
interviews in other places.
Uh certainly, if you reach out to me
with these uh exercises completed, like,
even if, you know, I do all my hiring,
there's tons of people who I know who
are hiring as well, and I'd be happy to
refer people as well.
>> OpenAI, [snorts]
Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel all use
this product to make their lives better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an ad product, and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSL, there's SCIM, there's RBA,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product, and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast.
On the next [snorts] topic, I mean, uh I
saw you're the the the area lead for
pre-training on Gemini, and I just
thought it might be interesting to hear
you give um
uh kind of like a high-level overview of
what pre-training is or in your words,
and maybe what are the the high-level
challenges in the area. I mean, we can
talk about that.
>> Yeah, so
there's there's quite a lot of work that
we do in pre-training. Um as an area
lead for it,
the specific things that my team is
responsible for delivering uh include uh
the flash model, the flashlight model.
These are models that get used for AI
overviews and AI mode in the search bar,
uh as well as some other uh 1P models
that are used by different orgs like ads
and YouTube.
Besides this, we're also key technical
POCs for the uh Google-Apple
partnership, uh and so we do technical
work there.
Those are the actual
like product-level deliverables
uh from my team.
Uh beyond that, we do research to make
sure that these deliverables are
state-of-the-art.
And also, we do general pre-training re-
research that contributes to the Pro
Series model as well.
And the nature of the research, I would
say generally breaks down into three
different verticals. There's
distillation, which I mentioned earlier.
There's what I like to call inference
co-design. So, uh
creating neural architectures that are
efficient
uh to run inference on. So, coming up
with the network topology, the shapes of
the matrices that the matmuls uh
uh use uh inside of uh
uh gating and linear layers for this
Transformer as well as the attention
shapes, num heads, that kind of thing.
So, that that is effectively utilizing
the hardware that you're serving on.
And then, the final
uh pillar here is new quantization
methods. And so,
quantization is just something that's uh
been near and dear to my heart that I've
been working on the research side for
ever since I joined Google, and it
really changes what's feasible for uh
the first two. So,
uh that's why,
you know, furthering the state of the
art in terms of how you can compress
models is is also a very important
pillar in the research that my team
does. Generally, uh
uh quantization uh refers to reducing,
in some sense, the size that the neural
nets take up uh in order to represent
their weights. So, typically, a neural
net, when you're training it, uh is
represented as a
uh series of numbers that make up the
matrices inside of the neural net uh
that are stored in FP32, 32-bit
floating-point weights.
Um it turns out that, when you do these
computations, you don't need all of that
extra precision to still maintain the
quality of your neural net. And you can,
with pretty simple methods, reduce the
precision at which you store these
weights down to 4-bits. So, uh all of a
sudden, this huge range of numbers uh
that we would take, you know, this float
32 to represent, uh something that gets
you down to like, you know, seven digits
of precision,
uh can,
you know, with somewhat high fidelity,
uh still be um
represented well by
4-bit ints, which, you know, just cover
this uh tiny range of like minus eight
to seven. And
um
it's it's kind of a miracle that you can
do this.
But what's even more of a miracle is
that you can apply these kind of
quantization transforms to the runtime
activations that the neural net
processes. And as soon as you do that,
the actual math that you're performing,
because you're taking much smaller
operands to your matmul than what you
were doing before,
the amount of electricity that it takes
to compute the neural net drops
significantly.
And what's interesting is that
like 99% of the total cost of operation
for
AI hardware comes from the
uh power that it takes to run these
chips. And so, if you can do these
operations, you could just make neural
nets run more cheaply, run more
efficiently.
That helps
uh
uh in terms of like serving more
requests, and it helps in terms of
latency.
So, the name of the game for quant
research is how do we push the frontier
beyond like this like four-bit range?
>> There's this take that I see on Twitter
all the time, um which is just talking
about MFU, and someone who's not in the
space, or model flops utilization.
Someone who's not in the space, they see
a number in the low 10s, and they think,
"Wow, they're wasting all of those GPU
resources."
Um I was curious if you could just
clarify that for people why a low MFU,
or I guess naively low, is actually not
low at all. And maybe also explain what
MFU is.
>> Yeah, so
when we compute MFU, you want to divide
the actual number of flops that the
neural net is performing here by the
total number of flops that the
accelerator could have done in the time
of your request. And so, in some sense,
this is giving us the
uh percent of time that we're usefully
utilizing the flops rate of the
accelerator. And to get to 100% MFU, you
would just need be need to be fully
utilizing uh the matmul unit of uh
whatever accelerator uh you're doing
here. So, it would just have to be doing
like a bunch of matmuls in a loop
uh without reading any memory or doing
any other operations.
That's not a very useful computation. Uh
and in practice,
neural nets have to apply activation
functions or do attention or write
intermediate outputs back to uh HBM. And
all of those different operations
will require utilizing the memory bus or
utilizing vector processing units
uh or simply they might be a
mathematical operations that
the underlying hardware performs more
slowly than they uh than uh it might
perform a matmul.
>> [snorts]
>> And so, all of those things contribute
to not running at the full speed that
the processor is rated at.
Uh and so, that's why you might not see
100% MFU all the time is cuz,
you know, part of the time your neural
net was, you know, reading and writing
to memory or part of the time it was
doing an operation that uh you know,
fundamentally runs slower than certain
other units on your
on your device. And
I think quite a bit of this inference
co-design work that I talked about
earlier is
across all of the different
um
capabilities of the chip. So, uh
communication to other chips,
um memory bandwidth, the the speed at
which we can read parameters from
memory,
flops, of course. Uh
this can be matmul flops. This can be
flops for processing uh
vectors. So, like things like doing
activations.
Uh all of these have different rates in
the hardware.
And a given computation isn't going to
match the natural hardware's rate
uh of each of those operations. So, when
you design a neural net, you want to be
able to choose shapes for this neural
net that fully saturate all of those
hardware units to get you as high of an
MFU as possible
um when you are doing uh inference here.
What makes this
more than just an algebra problem is
that those choices translate to
different quality outcomes when you
actually train this neural net.
So, the process of this kind of
inference co-design is how do we come up
with neural architectures that
scale predictably
have a good prediction, so are high
quality
and still
make the MFU as large as possible during
inference. And so, this kind of joint
optimization is what makes inference
co-design really fun.
Uh and also this kind of evergreen
problem because as the hardware changes
all of those relative constants of flops
to memory bandwidth to communication
bandwidth change and those will have
different implications to what's the
optimal neural net shape should be.
>> On another topic
Google has this idea of a spot bonus
where someone can kind of give you uh a
one-off
lump sum of money as a thank you for
like good performance. And I I saw on
your resume that Jeff Dean, the legend
himself, gave you a spot bonus. And you
know, if you can tell that story, I'd
love to hear why did he give you a spot
bonus?
>> Yeah, so that one actually was at the
very beginning of the Gemini program.
Uh he gave out a spot bonus to people
who
hopped on and launched the first version
of Bard. And like I had a you know a
very small contribution to a very very
large project at the time.
Uh I helped with uh SFT for
uh one of the first versions uh of
uh supervised fine-tuning for one of the
first versions of uh
Bard that got released like right, you
know.
The biggest lesson
out of
uh that experience was
you know, at that time
I was just doing like pure research in
um uh Google Brain.
And I was super focused on just how do I
maximize the number of first author
papers at uh NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR. And
I remember distinctly thinking like I I
had this instinct of like oh like, you
know, should I just keep my head down
and try to write more papers? And
Luckily at the time uh my my manager
Rohan Aneja, like he really encouraged
all of us to get involved in
uh you know, this space.
And
that was just the right motivation that
I needed to like roll up sleeves, do a
bunch of hyperparameter tuning and
engineering work to get uh this uh model
running on uh uh some like really old
TPUs to get some extra you know, cycles
in for for
uh SFT attempts.
That very small initial engagement that
was recognized by Jeff Dean, I I think
blossomed into more and more investments
on the LLM side by me and
ultimately led me to where I am today.
Uh so
yeah, I would say
you know, it it's less so about you
know, [snorts]
you know, how much that like SFT helped
the initial release and it's much more
about uh
uh recognizing that like
there's there's quite a bit of work,
some of it not glamorous, some of it
just like, you know, hyperparameter
tuning and,
uh, golfing the XLA compiler to make
your program fit in a certain memory
amount
that contributes to a wider business
goal that
is is really quite important for
getting involved in in very high-value
projects.
>> You've been working on Gemini for a
while now, and because it's a top
priority, there has to be some, you
know, incidents or war stories that
you've been involved in. So, I'm
curious, you know, what's your favorite,
uh, war story when working on Gemini?
>> So, I think my all-time favorite
would have to be
Flash 2.0.
Uh, so this one this one was quite a
challenge and a very long journey to get
there.
But,
uh, one of the
main things that we were optimizing for,
which which Flash 1.5 established, is
this category of very fast, low-latency
model
that's still
quite good. Um, and, you know,
in particular, it has to be fast because
it's it's used by search to serve,
uh,
responses in in AI mode, uh, very
quickly.
Because of that,
uh, for Flash 1.5 and before, we we
focused on dense models, which, uh,
allow you to respond very quickly.
Even though at the time we we knew about
MoE models and how they increase
capacity.
And so, I think, um,
one thing that like came up was, okay,
like
we sure would like to use this new
architecture, but it it's difficult to
just simply switch to an MoE because
what happens with an MoE is it it uses a
lot more parameters in general
and because it uses more parameters, it
takes up more HBM.
These chips that we serve on have a
finite amount of HBM, so you have to
shard the MOE across
multiple different chips. So, if you
have, you know, whatever NX birds then
you might chart it across N chips or,
you know, some factor of N.
And what this causes is a lot of
communication in the middle of the
model. When you have a token that needs
to be routed to an expert and that token
might live on the first TPU, but it
needs to go to the last TPU, that's a
lot of communication that you're
inducing in the forward pass. So, the
latency of this operation
like increases dramatically with N.
And
you know, the challenge with MOEs is
they increase N. So,
that that that like kind of really
bottleneck this approach.
And one interesting thing that happened
was we we definitely knew about pipeline
serving for a while.
It's just in the dense case
it never really ended up mattering. Like
I distinctly remember a very early
conversation I had with Sholto about it
and Sholto's like, "Oh yeah, you're like
so flop bound and so pipelining is just
not going to change your prefill
profile." And then he was right. I
tested it out and like then abandoned
the idea.
But what's interesting is
I I had a very small team at the time
and and one of my reports, Gangyan,
had a very nice idea. He was working
with Rahul Arya and a couple folks from
the Israel team at Google.
And that was to apply pipeline prefill
to MOEs.
And pipelining is
a technique where instead of
parallelizing
those N machines experts across those N
machines, you parallel layers across
those end machines. So, instead of on a
particular layer, you have to route
tokens from machine to machine, now one
layer does the computation for one
subset of your pre-fill request, and
then hands off the processed tokens to
the next machine to process the second
layer, and then the third layer, and the
fourth layer.
And
all of the experts can then stay
resident to a single machine or a
smaller set of machines. So,
what this does effectively is it changes
the communication pattern from something
that required a lot of token exchange on
every single layer to
something that's
actually can be hidden behind other
computation because you can do this
pipeline pre-fill across different parts
of your request.
So,
while layer two is working on the
first thousand tokens of your request,
layer one on the first chip is
processing
the second thousand tokens of your
request. So, it was a way of
breaking this HBM constraint by moving
layers across the machines rather than
moving experts across these machines.
And because of that, the communication
overhead has gone down, and all of a
sudden, MoE latency looks really
attractive now. This, you know, the the
Gemini 2.0 report says like it's an MoE
series of models, and the thing that
made that possible is, you know, or one
of the things that made that possible is
is this
you know, serving time innovation.
Dwarak and Reiner have an amazing post
about exactly this
optimization that you can write up in
the algebra of the scaling book. And
it's just a wonderful example of how
this kind of
change can
uh have really dramatic implications on
LLM quality. What really made Flash 2.0
rewarding is
this, you know, giant MoE decision. It
sounds like a small technical decision
at the time, but
people were really worried about whether
or not the latency of this MoE would
actually be reasonable. Luckily,
I was able to run like a very
transparent technical process to get to
the bottom of this. And by the end of
it, uh uh uh you know, we we made the
right call, uh but then we had to train
it. So,
this was a bigger model than we've ever
trained before at the flash scale, and
like we knew this would be the right
call, but it was just going to be 40
days of grueling work for like a really,
really small team. Like we probably had
like five people on the rotation for
training this model. I remember, you
know, all of us just kind of like
rotated day by day, handing off like,
you know,
all of this like SRE style work of uh
keeping the training job alive, which at
the time was was
a very interactive thing cuz uh you had
to make sure that everything was moving
stably, that, you know, you have tuned
data iterators that aren't slowing down
your job, that, you know, if there's
like a gap in the data somewhere or an
indexing issue, you have to like really
quickly put up a fix because it's, you
know, wasting all of this GPU time. Um
>> What about at night time and on the
weekends?
>> So, yeah, like I think, you know, for
those 40 days, we did not do a lot of
sleeping. Like we had to
like do like kind of these dual shifts
across like the Paris office and
Mountain View, and like the thing that
makes it so rewarding was when this
model came out, like around the same
time, uh DeepSeek V3 came out. And uh
the Wall Street Journal put out this
article that was like this giant red
scare article about how China's going to
take over AI with open source models and
I remember my friend sent me a
screenshot of this table of the LMSYS
Arena leaderboard. And you know, all the
way at the top right you've got
chat GPT and
and DeepSeek right behind it. And like,
oh, DeepSeek was trained for whatever
few million dollars, you know, and and
like they're right there.
And then my friend was like, oh, like
you know, Gemini is so behind cuz they
had, you know, a version of like I think
1.5 Pro or something in that table at
the very bottom.
And then I looked at it and was like,
oh, that's really interesting. I was
just looking at this leaderboard cuz we
just released a model and it definitely
doesn't look like that when you go to
the website. So, turns out there was
kind of some ill-written rows on the
Wall Street Journal article. And so now
if you go to that article today, you can
see, you know, what at the time was the
state of the art model
you know, Flash 2.0 thinking
up in the top right corner way far ahead
of DeepSeek V3.
Might be messing with the open source
narrative that they were trying to
publish there, but it was a really
important accomplishment for for the
team.
>> Last question for you is if you could go
back to yourself when you just graduated
college, I guess undergrad, and give
yourself some advice knowing what you
know now, what would you say?
>> You you got to chase the problems that
people are facing
like
in the world today. Like like go after
the challenges that people see in
everyday life and don't be afraid to
tackle a smaller part of this problem or
maybe a more menial sounding part of
this problem, even if it's not fancy
research math or something like that.
Like, trust that by working on what's
important, even if it's a smaller part
of a larger project for what's
important, you're going to get to see
what really matters in terms of moving
the frontier forward.
And it's it's this kind of, I guess,
humility maybe in your
problem approach that that you should
really be chasing.
Um that's one piece of advice. I think
the other bit that I would give, like
maybe as professional advice, perhaps,
would be
be the kind of co-worker
that
people would want to see succeed.
Uh and so, like what I mean by that is
there's this this like conception of
like
workplace psychopath or Machiavellian
leaders or or whatever, people who like
will do anything at all costs to get the
results they want. And they they they
they might be able to squeeze people to
get some short-term gain.
But,
you know, having interacted with a
variety of people professionally for so
long,
what is interesting to me is there have
been
a select few,
you know, one in particular is is
probably a very dear friend and and
mentor of mine, Todd Lipkin, who first
got me into computer science.
Um
that are just so
like kind and
like people that you can learn from
and uh
you know, someone that I can
follow and be successful by following.
That just genuinely inspire me to want
to help them succeed. Uh, and so in
particular, if you
are the kind of person who
helps people succeed in their projects,
comes up with projects that can leverage
other people's complementary skills in
ways that help them shine,
people will notice that. People will
want to contribute to
projects that you come up with in the
future
and in general will want to support you
going forward.
And so, you know,
you people can get really cynical
thinking about the game theory of how to
interact at work.
Uh, but I found that this kind of more
amicable approach
generally like it it creates like this
this deep sense of collaboration and
you know, willingness to help that like
is so important to get very large
projects that require multiple people
and multiple skill sets
uh, over the line.
And so,
yeah, I think if if I could give any
kind of like inner you know,
interpersonal feedback or professional
feedback or whatever to
earlier version of myself, it's it's to
be that guy. It's to to be the kind of
person that other people want to see
succeed.
>> I love that this advice combats the
cynical advice. And I also love that
your original post combats the doomer,
you know, permanent underclass stuff.
So, um, yeah, thank you so much for your
time. It's a lot of fun. Really
appreciate it.
>> Thanks for having me, Ryan.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you Do you any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on?
Please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebreaker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides. Um
this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units.
Um we're now working on the long journey
of building the tooling now. And so, if
you still want to pick one up, I've left
the late pledges open on Kickstarter, so
you can grab one there. I'll put a link
in the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast, and I'll see you
in the next episode.